<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the right honourable, the Lord Fairfax, and his councell of vvarre: the humble addresse of Henry Hammond.</title>
            <author>Hammond, Henry, 1605-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87044</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865047</idno>
  <idno type="VID">164905</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240914042</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing H607</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E540_18</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205766</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865047</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99865047e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87044)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 164905)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 84:E540[18])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the right honourable, the Lord Fairfax, and his councell of vvarre: the humble addresse of Henry Hammond.</title>
                  <author>Hammond, Henry, 1605-1660.</author>
                  <author>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, Baron, 1612-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Royston in Ivie-lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In this edition there is a period following "London" in the imprint, and the pagination continues to p.29.</note>
                  <note>Numerous errors in pagination, signature D mis-signed E, but pagination is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 30th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, --  Baron, 1612-1671 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">England and Wales. --  Army. --  Council --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:164905:1"/>
            <p>To the Right Honourable, THE LORD <hi>FAIRFAX, AND</hi> His COUNCELL Of WARRE: <hi>THE</hi> HVMBLE ADDRESSE <hi>OF</hi> HENRY HAMMOND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Royston</hi> in Ivie-lane. 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:164905:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:164905:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord, and Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving by the Weekly occurrences of your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, not onely taken notice of the weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty matters which you have of late chosen to be the subject of your Debates, such as never any Councell in this Kingdome are known to have taken into their cognizance, or consideration; but withall, discern'd the cheerfull and hospitable reception of one meane Persons advice, which pretended to have received some counsell from God to communicate to you: And having also as sincere a desire and zeale to your good, (testified by my daily prayers to God, that he wil incline your hearts to thoughts of true Christian meeknesse and charity) and consequently, as deep an interest in the due management of your Affaires, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others; and as great an assurance, that what I shall say to you, proceeds from a peaceable, and an humble spirit; and which tends more immediately to your welfare, and honour, both before God and man, than any thing which is knowne of late to have been represented to you: And lastly, having among you some of the neerest of my blond, whose eternall weale must needs be very deare and pretious to me; I am in the feare of God, and the profecution and discharge of my duty and conscience, desirous to make this short addresse to you, to desire you, in the name, and in the bowels of <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> and by all the obligations of Christian duty and Charity, to review some of the principles by which you seem to be acted, and whereon to ground the high en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprises which you have now in hand.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:164905:3"/>
            <p>And 1. whereas you seem to believe, that God by his Spirit hath put it into your hearts to do what hitherto you have done, and what now you professe to deliberate to doe further against His Majesty, and all others, who are now fallen into your hands; I beseech you to consider in the presence of that God, to whose directions and Spirit you pretend, what safe ground you have for so doing. For, I shall suppose that the plaine words of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are not that voice of the Spirit which is your onely guide in this matter: or if it be, I desire that Charity from you for my selfe and others, that you will point us out those Scriptures: and I must professe to believe you bound in duty to God, and man, and to your selves, to satisfie this desire, to produce that voice of the Spirit in the received Scriptures of God, which may say that to other Christians also which it appeares to doe to you. But if Gods Spirit be by you conceived to have spoken to you any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way than in, or by some part of the written Word; then my second request is, that you will declare to others the ground of this your perswasion, that you have received any such Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from God; that so that pretended <hi>Spirit</hi> may according to the rules prescribed by God in his acknowledged Word be tried and examined regularly, <hi>whether it be of God, or no?</hi> before the subject-matter of such Revelation be believed infallible, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly built upon by you as your warrant or principle of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting any thing. For, there are <hi>evill Spirits</hi> that come into the world, and which many times are by God permitted to seduce men, and that they may doe so the better, they constantly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to come from God, and assume divine Authority to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend and authorize their delusions; (a thing so ordinary in all Ages, that the Poet that would expresse the Imbroyling of a Kingdome, thinks he cannot doe it better then by bringing in <hi>Alecto,</hi> a <hi>Fury,</hi> with a Message from Heaven, to avenge such or such an injury.) And of these our Saviour forewarns us, and tells us, that <hi>we shall know them by their fruits;</hi> and so directs i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to judge of the truth of their pretensions by the goodnesse and commendablenesse, at least, justifiablenesse of their <hi>actions,</hi> and not to judge of their <hi>actions</hi> by their <hi>pretences.</hi> And besides chest <hi>evill spirits</hi> from without, there is also an <hi>evill spirit</hi> within, a great deale of disguised wickednesse in the heart of man, which when
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:164905:3"/>it remaines unmortified in those who believe themselves to be <hi>Gods chosen Saints, and taught by him,</hi> is very apt to be mistaken for an inclination of <hi>Gods Spirit,</hi> and <hi>a flame of zeale,</hi> when it is really the most contrary to it: and because there is so much dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, that what is not fetcht from the acknowledged Word of God, may thus flow from one of these contrary principles: my next request is, that it be considered, whether when <hi>an Angel from Heaven,</hi> in case he should <hi>teach any other Doctrine, than what had been by Saint</hi> Paul <hi>preached</hi> to his <hi>Galathians,</hi> were to be <hi>ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematized,</hi> and when the judgments are so fearfull, which are pronounced against them which <hi>shall adde to the Words of that Prophesie,</hi> which we now reteine under the title of the <hi>Apocalyps</hi> or <hi>Revelation</hi> (which being the last Writing which is knowne to be dictated by the <hi>Spirit,</hi> may very probably conteine a severe denuntiation against all those, who pretend to any <hi>Revelation</hi> or <hi>Prophesie</hi> after that, concerning the Christian Church) whether I say it be not a matter of fear and just apprehension, to all those, who shall affix or impose upon the Spirit of God (or pretend to be revealed to them from that) any matter of Doctrine or Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, which acknowledges not the Spirit of God speaking in the Scripture for its onely warrant or foundation. Or lastly, if from the Scriptures you conceive it may be proved, that any part of the <hi>Ʋnction</hi> mentioned there so farre belongs to you, that it shall surely <hi>lead you into all truth:</hi> then first, I beseech you to consider, whether you doe not oblige your selves by the same, or some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scripture to prove to others (and not onely your selves to be perswaded) that you are those speciall Saints of God, to whom that priviledge peculiarly belongs, and as clearly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate that all others who conceive that that Unction teaches them directly the contrary to that which you professe to be taught by it, are impious Persons possest with that deluding Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which I now desire you to beware of. And secondly, to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine whether this differencing of your selves from others, this bearing witnesse to your selves, and judging others (beside that it will looke like an act of most <hi>Pharisaicall</hi> presumption, and the very thing, which from <hi>Simon Magus</hi> downward, hath been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served in all Hereticks, calling themselves <hi>the Spirituall,</hi> and all others <hi>Animal, carnall Men)</hi> will not be also a great injustice at
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:164905:4"/>this time toward them who pretend not to learne any thing from this Unction, but what they receive from the Doctrine of the Gospel, in those Books, which have in effect, and in the last result, the testimony of God from Heaven, that they are his true infallible Word, and dictate of his Spirit; and which desire to make no other use of this to their owne advantage, but onely to preserve them in a quiet possession of what by Law belongs to them and a capacity of making good their Allegiance to Him, to whom they have often by Law been required to sweare it.</p>
            <p>A second principle which I must desire you to review, is that, upon which you conclude that God hath borne testimony to your Cause by the many Victories which he hath given you: this concluding of yours, first, proceeds upon a premise directly false in matter of fact. For, you say that the King by taking up Armes made His <hi>appeale to Heaven,</hi> which 'tis most certain that He never did, (but onely used a strength which God put in his hands to repell them, whom He look'd on as His Subjects declining their duty to Him, and invading the setled Lawes, and never referred the right of the Cause to be judged by the successe of His Armes) nor indeed could rationally have occasion to doe so, any more than any one of you would make such appeale, when a violent Person should invade, what you conceive to be your undoubted right; nor could He religioufly, or Christianly have done this, when those Lawes that allow'd of such appeales by <hi>Ordeals,</hi> or <hi>Duell,</hi> and the like, have been justly censured as unchristian and barbarous. Nay secondly, this concluding of yours will by the same reason infer that Christianity is not, and that Mahumetisme is the true Religion, because when the Turkes asserted one, and the Greek Church the other, and that difference begat a Warre betwixt them, 'tis cleare that the Turkes were successfull, and the Greeke Church was most fadly wasted and subdued by them, and so remaineth to this houre in that unreturn'd Captivity. Which will therefore be a fit opportunity to make you revert to the try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that Spirit (which inclines you thus to argue) by this touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone. 1. By considering and examining whether in the written Word any thing be more frequent and visible than the <hi>sufferings of Gods people,</hi> the <hi>shedding the bloud of the Sain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> the fasting all kind of contumelies on such, particularly that repreach of <hi>[you
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:164905:4"/>bloudy man]</hi> upon <hi>David,</hi> who was a <hi>King after Gods heart,</hi> the <hi>sending</hi> or permitting <hi>an Host against the daily sacrifice to cast down the truth to the ground, and to practice and prosper.</hi> 2. Whether it were not <hi>Rabshekeh's</hi> Argument against the Peoples adhering to their lawfull <hi>King Hezekiah,</hi> that his Masters Armes had been invincible. 3. Whether that saddest fate of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> who for conquering of Gods people, and others, was by God stiled <hi>his Hammer,</hi> and <hi>Battleaxe of the whole earth,</hi> may not be expected the finall lot of others also; first, to destroy men, and then to be cast out into the field, to inhabit among Beasts. 4. Whether it were not a crime complained of by the people of God, in those, which, when God was a <hi>little displeased,</hi> did as Adversaries, <hi>help forward their affliction.</hi> And 5. whether the Psalmist lay not the like ill character on all, who <hi>persecute those whom God hath smitten,</hi> and <hi>talke how they may vex them whom God hath wounded?</hi> By all which it is most evident, (without any necessity of desining or demonstrating any thing of the justice of the Cause) that most commonly the prosperity of Armes hath not been <hi>the lot of the</hi> most <hi>righteous,</hi> but that either the <hi>chastise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of the Sword is thought fit to be their <hi>discipline,</hi> or the comforts of peace (and not the triumphs of warre) their <hi>blessing</hi> in this life.</p>
            <p>The third principle is, your perswasion that the <hi>community of the People is the Suprome power, and that the KING is inferiour to them, and to them accountable for His breach of Trust, of which you now affirme Him guilty.</hi> In this procedure of yours, there be many things worthy of your serious pondering: As whether 1. by Scripture: or 2. by Reason: or 3. by Story of times it can be concluded, that the <hi>Supreme Power</hi> was ever by God put into the hands of the community of the People. For the first way of concluding it, (the testimony of Scripture) I cannot but take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of one place, which hath been produced to that purpose, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. Be <hi>subject to every humane Ordinance,</hi> or <hi>Creature,</hi> or <hi>Creation,</hi> &amp;c. This place I have some reason to believe to carry some weight with you, because it was 6 years since for the justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the Cause against the <hi>King's party,</hi> produced by a Person of great dexterity, That very Person, who hath now undertaken to justifie your late proceedings so farre as not onely to clear them
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:164905:5"/>from all blame, but also to pretend to <hi>demonstrate the honour and worth of them,</hi> and to lift them up to an high pitch, not onely, 1. of a <hi>blessed victory</hi> (the highest that Christians are appointed to aspire to) <hi>of overcomming evill by doing good:</hi> but 2. of <hi>calling to</hi> mens <hi>minds the unparellable example of the Lord Jesus Christ, who went downe into the Chambers of death, from thence to bring up with him a lost world:</hi> and 3. of being a <hi>lineament of the face of Divine goodnesse, in the doing good to so many, as well Enemies, as Friends:</hi> and 4. <hi>deserving that place at the table of honour, which the Roman Orator saith, all Nations bestowed on the Assertors of their Countries liberties,</hi> even <hi>next to the immortall Gods themselves:</hi> and 5. of <hi>imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating the method of the warfare of Heaven, and seeking to reconcile a Nation to themselves by not imputing their unthankefulnesse.</hi> The largnesse and exorbitancy of these expressions I was my selfe so amaz'd at, that I cannot but mention them to you (by the way) as matters of horrour, which like the Peoples acclamation to <hi>Herod,</hi> or the <hi>Lycaonians</hi> to <hi>Paul and Barnabas,</hi> if they beget not in you a just indignation with the latter, may very probably bring the just fate of the former upon you, <hi>to be eaten up with Wormes,</hi> (after you have been thus <hi>deified)</hi> now, that you have no other visible Enemy but your selves, and such Flatterers, (that I say no worse) to appeare against you, having craved your pardon for this not unseasonable excursion, I return now to the view of that Scripture, produced from Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> to prove <hi>Kings</hi> to be a <hi>creation</hi> or creature of men, and so their power to be derived from the People. To which I Answer, 1. that there is a fignall character in that very Text, that keeps it from concluding the <hi>supreme power</hi> to be <hi>originally</hi> in the <hi>People,</hi> not only by calling the <hi>King</hi> in the end of that Verse, <hi>Supreme;</hi> such as in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> divinity, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. are affirmed to be <hi>ordained of God,</hi> and so no <hi>humane Ordinance,</hi> but also by distinguishing the <hi>Governours,</hi> v. 14. from the <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Supreme,</hi> v. 13. by this that the <hi>Governours</hi> are <hi>sent by (i. e.</hi> have Commission from) the <hi>King,</hi> which might in like manner be also affirmed of the <hi>King,</hi> that He were sent by the <hi>People,</hi> if He were the Creature, or creation of them, but is not so much as intimated by that Apostle; but on the contrary, <hi>supremacy</hi> affixt to Him, and <hi>subjection</hi> commanded to be paid Him (not for the <hi>Peoples,</hi> but for the <hi>Lords sake)</hi> as subordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:164905:5"/>to, and <hi>mission</hi> from the <hi>King,</hi> is affirm'd of all other <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates.</hi> But then 2. to take away all colour of plea for <hi>popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy</hi> from this Text, it is to be observed what is the meaning of the Greek word in the New Testament, which is there rendred
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>ordinance,</hi> or <hi>creature,</hi> or <hi>creation.</hi> That word when it is set in its largnesse without any restraint, signifies generally <hi>all mankind,</hi> Gentiles, as well as Jewes. Thus <hi>[the creation]</hi> and <hi>[the world]</hi> are all one, and <hi>[all the ereation]</hi> (or <hi>every creature) Mar.</hi> 16.15. the same with <hi>[the whole world]</hi> in the beginning of that Verse, and <hi>[all Nations]</hi> in the parallel places of Saint <hi>Matthew</hi> and Saint <hi>Luke.</hi> And thus <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.19. <hi>[the expectation of the creature,</hi> or <hi>creation]</hi> is the hope which the <hi>heathen world</hi> had, that at the <hi>revelation</hi> of the gracious priviledges of the <hi>Messias,</hi> they <hi>(i.e.</hi> the <hi>Gentiles)</hi> also should be <hi>freed from the slavery of corruption</hi> (their villainous heathen sinnes) <hi>unto the liberty,</hi> &amp;c. that true liberty not from obedience to Superiours, but from slavery to lusts and passions, which Christ came to bestow upon us; And so when <hi>v.</hi> 22. 'tis added, that the <hi>whole creation groanes,</hi> &amp;c. the cleare meaning is, that the <hi>Gentiles</hi> as well as <hi>Jewes</hi> did thus, as might be evidenced at large. Agreeable to this notion of the <hi>whole crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or <hi>every creature,</hi> is this same phrase (with the addition of <hi>bumane,</hi> to take off all restraint, and to extend it as far as all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind) to be understood, and so the meaning of the precept of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> to his <hi>Jew-Christians</hi> is clearly this, and no more, that they must be <hi>obedient</hi> not onely to <hi>Christian</hi> Magistrates, but to <hi>Gentiles, Heathen</hi> also, (such as they should fall under in all their <hi>dispersions) i.e.</hi> to all whatsoever they were, and that <hi>for the Lords sake</hi> who constituted those Heathens also, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> saith. If to this it shall be objected, that by this way of interpreting, the precept will be extended so, as to subject us to <hi>all Heathens,</hi> and not onely to <hi>Magistrates:</hi> I answer, that this, which is the onely objection against this interpretation, is of little force, and is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered. 1. by observing the word <hi>[be subject]</hi> which relating to <hi>Magistrates</hi> will require our obedience to none, but those, as <hi>v.</hi> 17. when he commands to <hi>honour all,</hi> it must be understood, all to whom <hi>honour belongs;</hi> Superiours, not Inferiours: or as, when <hi>ch.</hi> 5.5. he commands them to be <hi>subject to one another,</hi> it must not be understood, that the <hi>Superiour</hi> must be subject to the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:164905:6"/>
               <hi>Inferiour,</hi> as the <hi>Inferiour</hi> to the <hi>Superiour,</hi> but as the nature of the duty inforces to interpret, the <hi>Inferiour</hi> to be subject to the <hi>Superiour</hi> onely: and 2. by the Apostles expresse enumeration of those to whom this obedience must be paid in the end of the Verse, <hi>to the King as Supreme;</hi> and then, <hi>v.</hi> 14. to <hi>Governours,</hi> as inferiour Magistrates <hi>sent by Him.</hi> That this is the full impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of that place, may (if there be any need) farther appeare by the occasion of the Apostles discourse, which was the confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the vile sect of Christians then calling themselves <hi>Gno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticks,</hi> (as a title of great perfection of <hi>knowledge</hi> in the Mysteries of Heaven) who taught the doctrine of <hi>liberty</hi> and manumission to <hi>Christian Subjects</hi> or <hi>Servants,</hi> from heathen (yea and <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian) Masters,</hi> and <hi>Kings;</hi> To which false doctrine of theirs this Exhortation thus interpreted is directly contrary (and cannot otherwise be pertinent to it) and very coherent to that Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition in the 12 <hi>ver.</hi> immediately preceding, of <hi>having their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation good among the Gentiles, that they might not speake ill of them as evill Doers;</hi> which they would be justly apt to doe, in case they should withdraw their obedience to their lawfull Princes, as soone as they were become Christians; which, by the way, laies a very ill character upon those, who by pretence of <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity,</hi> or <hi>piety,</hi> seeke, or claime to themselves any other <hi>liberty,</hi> than what by the <hi>Lawes</hi> under which they are bome, doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festly belong unto them.</p>
            <p>Having thus farre enlarged to cleare that testimony of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and not knowing of any other which is thought favourable to your pretension, I shall, in stead of retorting the multitude of plaine places directly opposite, which will abundantly take away all force from this: proceed next to the second plea, that of <hi>Reason.</hi> And there I shall desire you to consider, 1. Whether if <hi>Adam</hi> had never fallen, and his posterity remained in the same <hi>innocence,</hi> they would not yet have been capable of <hi>positive pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts</hi> in order to civill life; and consequently, whether in reason some one or more men should not have had superiority over all others, Parents over Children, and the like; and to this purpose, whether the divers Orders, and subordination of the Angels, that never fell, be not an evidence that even in state of innocence, God designed superiority, not equality. But then 2. The passions of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:164905:6"/>men being through sin grown irregular, and so needing Rules and Lawes, and Rulers and Law-makers, it was both reasonable, that God should, and is most certaine that he did designe and appoint Government (as appears by what is said by God to the first Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and second Man, to <hi>Eve. Gen.</hi> 3.16. and to <hi>Cain, Gen.</hi> 4.7.) and so gave not all men that freedome which is the supposed foundation of that doctrine, which places <hi>supreme power in the People.</hi> And of any rationall person that yet thinks he did give this freedome to all mankind; I should but aske this one que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion, Whether ever any man were by God or nature invested with power of his owne life; I meane, with power to take away his owne life, or to kill himselfe? In every thing else man may be believed to have a <hi>power</hi> over himselfe, over his <hi>body,</hi> to cut or lance it, when that is for his turne, and particularly over that <hi>freedome</hi> which naturally belongs to him; whatever the degree of that be, a man may by act of his owne will, part with it irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versibly. Thus might the <hi>Jew</hi> under Gods owne government, give himself up wholly into the power of his <hi>Master.</hi> and by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his <hi>care bored</hi> thorough, become from a <hi>Free-man,</hi> a <hi>Slava for ever,</hi> and generally thorow the whole world the course hath been the same, that he which if most free hath power over his owne liberty so to divest himself of it, as that it shall never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert to him againe; and our <hi>Saviour</hi> that is thought to have brought <hi>liberty</hi> into the world, doth yet, by the quality of most of his <hi>precepts,</hi> given to Christians by himselfe and his Apostles, marke out this condition of <hi>subjection</hi> to them, as that under which they were generally to live, and from which the <hi>Christian profession</hi> should be so farre from freeing them, that the strict practice of <hi>obedience</hi> to heathen Rulers or Masters, is oft prescri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed as a speciall meanes to advance Christs maine end, to mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie and promote the Gospel. But for power over a mans owne <hi>life</hi> no man can be believed to be borne with it, for if he were, he might then as lawfully <hi>kill himselfe</hi> (and if he might doe it <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,</hi> there are many cases which might make it <hi>prudent</hi> for him to do it at some times) as pul out an aking tooth, or dispose of his <hi>liberty</hi> or estate out of his owne possession; a thing which no Christian hath ever thought lawfull, but made this <hi>feloniae de se,</hi> this self-murther, or felony against ones selfe, a crime, as contrary
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:164905:7"/>to the sixt Commandement, as the <hi>killing of any other man.</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving proceeded thus farre, I shall now take that for granted, which, that I know of, is denied by none, I am sure, which is not denied in the publisht scheme of the designed <hi>Representative, viz.</hi> that the <hi>supreme power</hi> includes the <hi>power of life,</hi> (I meane not such an <hi>arbitrary</hi> power of killing whom they please without sinne, but a power of putting capitall Malefactors to death, and so a <hi>power</hi> over every (call it Subjects or Free-mans) <hi>life</hi> in case of capitall crime) And the granting of this (as 'tis too visible that it is by you a granted truth) being added to the former, doth to me irrefragably conclude, that the <hi>supreme power</hi> neither is, nor can be in the <hi>community of the People,</hi> or in their <hi>Representative,</hi> by force meerly of their <hi>originall</hi> or <hi>naturall liberty;</hi> The inference is cleare, because the <hi>power of life</hi> which is part of the <hi>Supremacy,</hi> is not part of that <hi>naturall liberty,</hi> and therefore is neither inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent naturally in that <hi>community of men,</hi> (which is but, in other words, so many particular men together, indow'd with that <hi>power</hi> (and no more) which every man hath <hi>singly</hi> over himself) nor consequently by them communicable to any <hi>Representative.</hi> And by this also it appeares, that <hi>supreme Magistracy,</hi> whereso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever 'tis truly placed, is the <hi>ordinance,</hi> and <hi>creation of God,</hi> (who alone hath <hi>power</hi> of all mens <hi>lives</hi>) and not of <hi>man,</hi> who hath no <hi>power</hi> of his <hi>owne,</hi> much lesse of any others life, any farther then he is a <hi>Representative,</hi> or <hi>Proxy,</hi> or <hi>Deputy of God,</hi> who hath that <hi>Power,</hi> not of the <hi>People,</hi> who have it <hi>not.</hi> For it is possible I may put you in mind of an evident truth, which perhaps you have not taken notice of; That, as the <hi>originall</hi> of <hi>Government</hi> in any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar place cannot be imagined to be by any more than two waies, Either <hi>Gods designment,</hi> or the <hi>Peoples act;</hi> so in either of those two cases 'tis <hi>God</hi> onely, and not the <hi>People,</hi> that gives the <hi>power of the Sword,</hi> or <hi>power of Life</hi> to the <hi>Governour;</hi> when <hi>God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe</hi> sets a <hi>King</hi> over men, 'tis so cleare that <hi>he</hi> thus impowers <hi>that King,</hi> that that need not be proved; and when the <hi>commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of a People</hi> (suppose in the <hi>Originall,</hi> ten men in the <hi>freedome of nature) chuse</hi> one of themselves, or more to rule over them; 'tis cleare, they doe not invest him with more <hi>power</hi> than them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves had; &amp; that he that was thus chosen by them, hath the <hi>power of life</hi> over any of them (which they single, or all together in the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:164905:7"/>
               <hi>community</hi> had not) must needs come from some other, and not from them; and if you will know from whom it comes, I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, that it comes from <hi>Gods appointment</hi> (for the oeconomy of the world) that the supreme Magistrate shall as his Deputy have this <hi>power</hi> from <hi>God</hi> communicated to him, as an endowment ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to that <hi>power</hi> which is design'd to protect, and governe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. And in case it were the act of the <hi>People,</hi> and not of <hi>God</hi> immediately, that designes or <hi>nominates</hi> the <hi>Person</hi> to that Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, yet doth not this <hi>nomination</hi> bestow this <hi>power,</hi> but <hi>God</hi> who alone <hi>hath</hi> that power, bestowes it on him who is thus <hi>nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> In this case all that the <hi>People</hi> bestow, or part with by their act is their <hi>owne liberty,</hi> or that part of it of which they volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily divest themselves, that they may by <hi>obedience</hi> empower him, whom they have set over them; &amp; that they may reasonably part with for that greater benefit of <hi>protection</hi> from him, which, while he is obeyed by all, he may by their united <hi>obedience</hi> to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands be able to afford them, and could not probably without it; now this giving up their <hi>liberties</hi> to one, or more, makes that man, or men a <hi>Ruler</hi> over them; and being a <hi>Ruler,</hi> to him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs (derived from <hi>God,</hi> not from <hi>them</hi>) that <hi>power of life, and death,</hi> which Gods forementioned decree hath enstated on the <hi>supreme power,</hi> or <hi>Ruler;</hi> who is therefore in that relation (of <hi>Avenger for wrath,</hi> or punishment) stiled by the <hi>Apostle, the Minister of God, Rom.</hi> 13. and not of the <hi>People.</hi> By this it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares that (for the originall of power) the utmost that comes from the <hi>People,</hi> is that of which they have the <hi>power,</hi> till by some act of Gods, or their owne, they have parted with it, the liberty or power of their <hi>Persons</hi> (or in some sort and degree, as they shall part with it, of their <hi>bodies,</hi> or <hi>possessions</hi> in like manner) but not of their <hi>lives;</hi> For that other is of an higher origination; and therefore, supposing the <hi>power</hi> they had parted with, should, upon any emergent, revert to them againe, yet the <hi>power of life and death,</hi> or of the <hi>Sword</hi> can never revert, because it never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from them, but as the <hi>soule</hi> that came from <hi>God</hi> doth at the falling of the <hi>body</hi> back to its elements, or earth, from which it was first taken, <hi>returne to the hands of God that gave it,</hi> so the <hi>power of life,</hi> the <hi>prerogative</hi> first, and then the <hi>gift</hi> or investiture of <hi>God,</hi> must at the dissolution of any Government, and the sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:164905:8"/>
               <hi>reverting</hi> to its principles againe, returne to its proper fountaine, to <hi>God,</hi> and none but him. And to imagine it to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve to the community of the people, is the same unreasonable, as to conceive the <hi>immortall soule,</hi> that one beame of <hi>divinity</hi> (as this <hi>power of life and death</hi> is another) to accompany the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casse to the grave also. I have insisted the longer on this to make the mistake the more palpable, and the more impossible not to be discerned by you; and if I could foresee any colour of reason, that could possibly pretend against this evidence, I should yet enlarge yours, and my owne trouble, to discover it; but being, I professe, unable to mention any thing, which the grounds, which are already laid, have not prevented: I shall now proceed to the third and last way of examining this truth.</p>
            <p>By the history of times, and there I shall be forced to retract, at least to suspend the acknowledging of that, which, that I might examine it by reason, I was willing to <hi>suppose,</hi> but not <hi>grant,</hi> and shall now demand,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether by any anthentick <hi>story</hi> it appeares, that there e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver were any Nation or People in the world, who can be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed or proved to have had this <hi>supreme power</hi> vested in the whole <hi>community originally,</hi> or from their first comming toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? or if so, whether <hi>Gods</hi> judgment so visibly interposed, and the example of his instituting of <hi>Judges,</hi> and of <hi>Kings,</hi> (neither of them accountable to the People) be not to be preferred before all such presidents?</p>
            <p n="2">2. If 'twere granted, that in some <hi>one,</hi> or more places the <hi>power</hi> hath been <hi>originally</hi> in the People, yet it will never appeare by the originalls of <hi>all,</hi> or of <hi>this</hi> Kingdome, that in <hi>all</hi> or in <hi>this</hi> it was so; or if men will still <hi>opiniate,</hi> and affirme against the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of the <hi>Lawes,</hi> and <hi>constitution</hi> of this Kingdome, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst those <hi>Oaths</hi> which have for so many yeares acknowledged the seat of the <hi>Supremacy in the King,</hi> and not in the <hi>People;</hi> yet that, which is so false in matter of fact, being taken for truth also, there will againe be matter of inquiry, in point of <hi>reason,</hi> which will deserve your farthermost serious pondering:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether, after that the <hi>People</hi> have upon deliberation, and from <hi>choice</hi> intrusted some <hi>one</hi> or <hi>more</hi> Persons (in any certaine course of <hi>succession</hi> by <hi>Law</hi> designed) to <hi>rule</hi> over them, and after
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:164905:8"/>the <hi>Lang</hi> hath declared the <hi>person</hi> of that <hi>Supream Magistrate</hi> not to be <hi>accountable,</hi> but his <hi>Ministers</hi> only, (which may be a <hi>pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> of State, more advantagious to a peoples peace, then pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly is well understood) whether, I say, in this case any number of men whatsoever, can, upon any pretence, <hi>re-call</hi> that <hi>Trust,</hi> and <hi>void</hi> that <hi>Law,</hi> by which that King, and His Heires for ever, were constituted the <hi>Ruler</hi> of them? or if they might, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this were not most contrary to the <hi>end</hi> of all Government, <hi>quiet,</hi> and <hi>peace,</hi> and probably the parent of all <hi>confusion</hi> in the world, which is much worse than the <hi>hardest subjection?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay 2. if it should be ganted still, that the <hi>community of people</hi> have power to <hi>recall,</hi> or <hi>void that trust,</hi> yet 'twill be matter of more than doubt againe, whether at <hi>this</hi> time in <hi>this</hi> Kingdome there be any way for the <hi>whole community</hi> to act, or whether it can by any man be reasonably believed, that what is <hi>now</hi> done, is <hi>acted</hi> by the <hi>community of the People?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For if (to that purpose) it be conceived, that the <hi>House of Commons</hi> is (or that the two Houses together are) the <hi>Represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative</hi> of <hi>all</hi> the <hi>People;</hi> Then first, it is to be considered that there is a great number of men in this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> that are <hi>not</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented by <hi>these,</hi> and who never put (nor can by any interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation be thought to have put) into their hands that <hi>Power,</hi> which is supposed to be in every free <hi>Commoner</hi> in this Kingdome. 2. That you your selves have exprest your opinion, that this, which now is, is an <hi>unequall Representative,</hi> and have on that consideration thought your selves obliged to <hi>propound</hi> another Forme. 3. 'Tis sure, that (whatever <hi>possibly might</hi> have been) yet they, that have ever till this time chosen <hi>Knights</hi> or <hi>Burgesses</hi> to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> did never actually put into their hands, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their <hi>Representatives, all</hi> that <hi>power,</hi> which (in this case of the <hi>Peoples</hi> being the <hi>Supreme Power</hi>) is naturally supposed to be vested in them, but only a <hi>power</hi> of doing those things, for which the Writ (sent out under the <hi>Broad Seal</hi>) did command them to be returned, <hi>i.e. to consult with the King of the difficult affaires of the Kingdome,</hi> not to <hi>settle any part of it without, or against Him.</hi> And 4. 'Tis clear, that in such an acknowledged conjuncture of time as this is, a <hi>small</hi> (farre lesse) <hi>part</hi> of those that were <hi>returned</hi> by the Countries, cannot be said to be that <hi>entire</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:164905:9"/>or body, by which the <hi>whole community</hi> is represented; Or if it be said, that the <hi>godly People of the Land,</hi> who by <hi>Petitions</hi> to the <hi>Generall,</hi> the <hi>Lord Fairfax</hi> have exprest their desires, that <hi>Justice</hi> be executed upon those, whom they call <hi>Delinquents,</hi> are to be reputed as the <hi>community of the People:</hi> then first, it will be clear, that those that have so <hi>Petitioned</hi> (beside, that they are most of the body of the <hi>Army</hi>) are not the thousandth part of the people of this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and therefore cannot by any rule of Judgement or Estimation be reputed as the whole <hi>Community;</hi> and if this <hi>president</hi> might be admitted, that a <hi>few</hi> persons, under the title of the <hi>Godly,</hi> may pretend to the right of the <hi>whole,</hi> tis very well worth foreseeing, how <hi>dangerous</hi> such <hi>examples</hi> may prove to the <hi>peace</hi> of Posterity. 2. All the evidence of their <hi>godlinesse</hi> that we can perceive, is only their desiring <hi>liberty</hi> for themselves and others, and therefore <hi>Justice</hi> on those who sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d in their way to that <hi>liberty;</hi> and I conceive it demonstrable that a quiet <hi>submission</hi> and <hi>obedience,</hi> and a desire not to cast off their <hi>duty,</hi> but still to continue under it, rather then to be their own <hi>carvers,</hi> or contrivers of <hi>liberty,</hi> is a farre surer signe of <hi>true god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse.</hi> And thirdly, there hath yet been no fair indifferent meanes used to know whether there be not farre greater numbers of such <hi>godly</hi> meek men, who would rather desire that the KING should be restored to His Government, then that any course should be taken by any, <hi>without,</hi> or <hi>against the</hi> KING. And the plain truth is, that if you will go on in the course you are in, and yet desire freely to appear, and be accounted the <hi>Conservers,</hi> and not <hi>Conquerours</hi> of the <hi>liberty</hi> of your Country-men, if you will not impose upon the people, as you say <hi>Kings</hi> have done; No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be more sutable to those <hi>pretences,</hi> then to <hi>declare mast publickly,</hi> that it shall be free for every man to <hi>subscribe,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he doth desire this totall <hi>change</hi> by you tendred in the draught of your <hi>Representative,</hi> or the continuance of the present established Government, (with an assurance of your submission thereunto.) 4. 'Tis (upon supposition that all <hi>power</hi> is <hi>originally</hi> in the <hi>People</hi>) most undeniable and clear, that nothing but the <hi>consent</hi> of each person (at least of a <hi>major part</hi> of the whole being convoked together) can divest any one, or more men of that their supposed <hi>Originall right;</hi> and consequently, that other mens
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:164905:9"/>saying that they are not <hi>Godly,</hi> and that themselves are so, can never exclude them from their <hi>Birthright;</hi> By which it will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly be concluded, that all those that have adhered to the KING all this time, or that favour'd the <hi>Vot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of the two Houses,</hi> which resolved the KING's late Concessions at <hi>Newport</hi> to be a fit ground of peace (whatsoever consure or brand is by you set upon them) are as much to be considered to the making up the <hi>community</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> as any others. And if so. Let it then be considered by all equall minded men, what a <hi>violation</hi> it is of those <hi>Rights,</hi> which you pretend to vindicate, what an invasion of the <hi>naturall freedome</hi> of your Brethren (by you acknowledged, the <hi>inheritance</hi> of <hi>each</hi> man) to force them against their <hi>wills,</hi> with their very great incommodation and detriment, to <hi>revert</hi> to that <hi>liberty,</hi> which is by you supposed to belong to all <hi>naturally,</hi> but without which we of this Nation have happily lived, under the farre greater advantages of <hi>Regall government.</hi> And yet so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to this <hi>principle</hi> have you now proceeded, that when you have thus throwne us back into our first <hi>chaos</hi> againe, onely that you may reduce our <hi>liberty,</hi> you then immediately by your <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentative</hi> so bind us up, that we are not permitted, upon what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever emergency, to cast our selves into any <hi>new forme,</hi> although the exchange should appeare never so advantageous, and gainfull to us; which besides that, it is an evidence of your inward <hi>feare,</hi> that the change now designed will be soone repented of againe, is certainly so farre from being an <hi>enlarging,</hi> that it is the <hi>retren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching</hi> of our <hi>liberty,</hi> and denying us that <hi>freedome,</hi> of which the most <hi>barbarous</hi> and the most <hi>civilized</hi> People have been equally partakers, when subjection seemed better for their turnes. As beside the examples of the <hi>Servants</hi> in <hi>Exodus,</hi> which are there supposed sometimes to preferre their servitude to their Masters before the priviledge of the <hi>Sabbaticke yeare,</hi> we find practised by the <hi>Campanians,</hi> who voluntarily cast themselves at the feet, and surrendred themselves into the <hi>power</hi> of the <hi>Romans,</hi> to purchase thereby that right of being <hi>protected</hi> by them; &amp; by many <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> in <hi>Appian,</hi> who sent <hi>Embassadours</hi> to <hi>Rome</hi> on purpose to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition the favor of being received into the number of their <hi>subjects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have insisted the longer upon this, in obedience to your owne <hi>invitation;</hi> which was also a great <hi>motive</hi> and <hi>encouragement</hi> to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:164905:10"/>make this whole <hi>addresse</hi> to you, and gives me assurance of your kind <hi>reception</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>The last principle to be review'd is this, That there having been much <hi>bloud</hi> spilt in this Kingdome in the late Warres, there must now be some <hi>sacrifice</hi> offer'd to <hi>God (i. e.</hi> some more <hi>bloud</hi> shed) for the <hi>expiation</hi> of that sinne of <hi>bloudguiltinesse,</hi> before <hi>God</hi> can be <hi>pacified,</hi> or <hi>reconciled</hi> to the <hi>Land.</hi> On which particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, it will first be worth your serious enquiry, how it should ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare that that great issue of <hi>bloud,</hi> let out in the late Warres (which hath with great reason been lookt on, as the sharpest of <hi>Gods plagues,</hi> and the saddest part of <hi>punishment</hi> of the former sinnes of this Nation) is now the maine, and onely <hi>sinne</hi> of the Land, with which God is not <hi>reconciled:</hi> Or 2. if it were suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to be so, yet how it can be thought that a <hi>generall Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of that sinne, an <hi>humiliation</hi> before God for it, through the whole Land, and a <hi>resolution</hi> never to <hi>spill one drop</hi> more, were not a more <hi>Christian</hi> probable meanes to <hi>pacifie God,</hi> than the proceeding in cold bloud to the <hi>effusion</hi> of <hi>more:</hi> The <hi>bloud</hi> of <hi>men</hi> being never thought a fit sacrifice for any, but the evill Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; and <hi>peaceable-mindednesse,</hi> and <hi>charity,</hi> and the <hi>contrite heart</hi> being the speciall, if not onely <hi>sacrifices,</hi> which we find mention'd in the Gospel. Or 3. how it can appeare that if <hi>God</hi> require any such <hi>sacrifice,</hi> you, or any but those whom the knowne Lawes of the Land have placed in a Tribunall (and that legally erected for <hi>such cognizances</hi>) have any right to put your selves into the office of <hi>Gentile Priests,</hi> as the onely Persons appointed to <hi>slay that sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice.</hi> Nay 4. it will be worth your observing, that <hi>Christ</hi> dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed the <hi>office</hi> of a <hi>Judge,</hi> and thereby rendred very unfit for any of you to put your selves unto that <hi>office</hi> by vertue of no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther title, but that of being his <hi>Disciples.</hi> And lastly, it is worth your saddest thought, Whether by your present <hi>Councell,</hi> and the <hi>necessity</hi> by you supposed of <hi>changing</hi> the <hi>former Government,</hi> it doe not now appeare, that the <hi>defence</hi> of the <hi>established Lawes</hi> was on the KING's part the occasion of His taking <hi>Armes,</hi> and on <hi>Your</hi> parts, the designe of <hi>altering</hi> those <hi>Lawes,</hi> and intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing <hi>others</hi> more sutable to your inclinations. And if now by a <hi>civill</hi> or <hi>martiall</hi> course, in an <hi>arbitrary</hi> way of triall, contrary to the <hi>Lawes</hi> established, it should be by you thought fit to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:164905:10"/>to <hi>bloud</hi> against those whom engagements have been for the <hi>defence</hi> of those <hi>establisht Lawes:</hi> Let it be consider'd, how <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politick</hi> this may be, and what matter of <hi>discouragement</hi> to all that shall be intrusted with the managery, or <hi>defence</hi> of future <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment:</hi> Which single consideration will, I hope, abate much of your designed <hi>severity.</hi> But if <hi>God</hi> should permit you to go on undisturb'd to the <hi>shedding</hi> of <hi>more bloud,</hi> as the <hi>Jewes</hi> did from other lower acts to the <hi>crucifying their King:</hi> How possible were it, not onely that this should prove the provoking of <hi>God</hi> to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver you up for ever to your owne hearts</hi> lusts, but be to the whole <hi>Nation</hi> a <hi>filling up the measure of our iniquities,</hi> and the forerunner of all the <hi>calamities,</hi> that can be fall a People.</p>
            <p>Having mention'd the <hi>weaknesse,</hi> and <hi>falliblenesse</hi> of these few <hi>principles,</hi> I shall leave you to the farther consideration of the <hi>frailnesse,</hi> and <hi>danger</hi> of those <hi>superstructures,</hi> which shall be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected on any, or all of these. And if there were never a <hi>God</hi> in the world to avenge them, yet the experience now before your eyes, how easie it is for <hi>principles</hi> taken up for mens present <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages</hi> to prove within a while most <hi>disadvantageous,</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious to them (as the <hi>weapons</hi> of a <hi>disarmed man</hi> turn'd into his <hi>owne breast</hi>) may infuse into you that <hi>feare</hi> and <hi>temper,</hi> that <hi>cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and <hi>moderation,</hi> and timely <hi>wisdome,</hi> which the Authour of this Addresse may be otherwise too unskilful to <hi>impresse</hi> on you: Who yet, if he might any way be usefull to you, doth professe to be ready to contribute his utmost endeavour to your service, if it be but thereby to demonstrate to you, how <hi>just</hi> it is for him (and what a <hi>duty,</hi> and <hi>obligation</hi> of <hi>charity</hi> toward you) to intercede daily at the <hi>throne of grace,</hi> that <hi>God</hi> would <hi>mollifie</hi> your hearts toward the KING, and all His <hi>conscientious faithfull</hi> Subjects, or else interpose his <hi>hand,</hi> to rescue His <hi>Royall Person</hi> out of your <hi>power;</hi> believing confidently, that, if God have any remainders of <hi>mercy</hi> for this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> or the true <hi>Protestant profession</hi> in it, he will in his good time heare and answer this prayer of all true <hi>Englishmen,</hi> and among them of</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Jan.</hi> 15. 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Lordships humble Servant, <hi>H. HAMMOND.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>